<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Christopher Prener</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Christopher Prener</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2017-2019 Christopher G. Prener</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Christopher Prener</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>/talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Your privacy is important to us. It is Christopher Prener&#39;s policy to respect your privacy regarding any information we may collect from you across our website, &lt;a href=&#34;https://chris-prener.github.io,&#34;&gt;https://chris-prener.github.io,&lt;/a&gt; and other sites we own and operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;information-we-collect&#34;&gt;Information We Collect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We only ask for personal information when we truly need it to provide a service to you. We collect it by fair and lawful means, with your knowledge and consent. We also let you know why we’re collecting it and how it will be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We only retain collected information for as long as necessary to provide you with your requested service. What data we store, we’ll protect within commercially acceptable means to prevent loss and theft, as well as unauthorised access, disclosure, copying, use or modification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclosure-of-personal-information-to-third-parties&#34;&gt;Disclosure of personal information to third parties&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site is supported by third-party providers to facilitate hosting and analytics. These include DNS management, web hosting via GitHub Pages, and Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will comply with government and law enforcement requests for data, as required by law, in connection with any actual or prospective legal proceedings, or in order to establish, exercise or defend our legal rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not sell or rent your personal information to marketers or third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cookie is a small piece of data that our website stores on your computer, and accesses each time you visit, so we can perform certain functions and understand how you use our site. We use third-party cookies to enable the website analytics using Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not wish to accept cookies from us, you should instruct your browser to refuse cookies from &lt;a href=&#34;https://chris-prener.github.io,&#34;&gt;https://chris-prener.github.io,&lt;/a&gt; understanding that we may be unable to provide you with generated Terms of Service and Privacy Policy statements without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-this-policy&#34;&gt;About this Policy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This privacy policy only covers Christopher Prener&#39;s own collecting and handling of data. We work with third-party providers and cannot accept responsibility or liability for their respective privacy practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our website may link to external sites that are not operated by us. Please be aware that we have no control over the content and practices of these sites, and cannot accept responsibility or liability for their respective privacy policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are free to refuse our request for your personal information, with the understanding that we may be unable to provide you with some of your desired services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your continued use of our website will be regarded as acceptance of our practices around privacy and personal information. If you have any questions about how we handle user data and personal information, feel free to contact us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This policy is effective as of 15 August 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on a privacy policy generated by GetTerms.io&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Terms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By accessing the website at &lt;a href=&#34;http://slu-soc1120.github.io,&#34;&gt;http://slu-soc1120.github.io,&lt;/a&gt; you are agreeing to be bound by these terms of service, all applicable laws and regulations, and agree that you are responsible for compliance with any applicable local laws. If you do not agree with any of these terms, you are prohibited from using or accessing this site. The materials contained in this website are protected by applicable copyright and trademark law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Use License&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is licensed under a &lt;a href=&#34;/license&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC-BY 4.0) License&lt;/a&gt;. You are free to &lt;strong&gt;share&lt;/strong&gt; (copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format) and &lt;strong&gt;adapt&lt;/strong&gt; (remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even commercially). The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, you must provide &lt;strong&gt;attribution&lt;/strong&gt; (you must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made). You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This license applies only to the &lt;strong&gt;content&lt;/strong&gt; of the site and does not apply to Hugo (released under an &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/about/license/&#34;&gt;Apache 2.0 License&lt;/a&gt;) or the Academic Theme (released under an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic/blob/master/LICENSE.md&#34;&gt;MIT License&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The materials on Christopher Prener&#39;s website are provided on an &amp;lsquo;as is&amp;rsquo; basis. Christopher Prener makes no warranties, expressed or implied, and hereby disclaims and negates all other warranties including, without limitation, implied warranties or conditions of merchantability, fitness for a particular purpose, or non-infringement of intellectual property or other violation of rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, Christopher Prener does not warrant or make any representations concerning the accuracy, likely results, or reliability of the use of the materials on its website or otherwise relating to such materials or on any sites linked to this site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Limitations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no event shall Christopher Prener or its suppliers be liable for any damages (including, without limitation, damages for loss of data or profit, or due to business interruption) arising out of the use or inability to use the materials on Christopher Prener&#39;s website, even if Christopher Prener or a Christopher Prener authorized representative has been notified orally or in writing of the possibility of such damage. Because some jurisdictions do not allow limitations on implied warranties, or limitations of liability for consequential or incidental damages, these limitations may not apply to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Accuracy of materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The materials appearing on Christopher Prener&#39;s website could include technical, typographical, or photographic errors. Christopher Prener does not warrant that any of the materials on its website are accurate, complete or current. Christopher Prener may make changes to the materials contained on its website at any time without notice. However Christopher Prener does not make any commitment to update the materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Prener has not reviewed all of the sites linked to its website and is not responsible for the contents of any such linked site. The inclusion of any link does not imply endorsement by Christopher Prener of the site. Use of any such linked website is at the user&#39;s own risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Modifications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Prener may revise these terms of service for its website at any time without notice. By using this website you are agreeing to be bound by the then current version of these terms of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Governing Law&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These terms and conditions are governed by and construed in accordance with the laws of Missouri and you irrevocably submit to the exclusive jurisdiction of the courts in that State or location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generated by GetTerms.io&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
