<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Overview | Christopher Prener</title>
    <link>/resources/students/</link>
      <atom:link href="/resources/students/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Overview</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2017-2019 Christopher G. Prener</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>/resources/students/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising Overview</title>
      <link>/resources/students/overview-advising/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/overview-advising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This section contains a few short articles that are primarily directed towards students who my &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/advising-role/&#34;&gt;advisees&lt;/a&gt; or who may want to request a &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/letters/&#34;&gt;letter of recommendation&lt;/a&gt; from me. I also have some advice about &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/internships/&#34;&gt;internships&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coursework Overview</title>
      <link>/resources/students/overview-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/overview-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This section contains a few short articles that are primarily directed towards students who are taking a class with me. I&#39;ve included tips for navigating some of the challenges of &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/little-things/&#34;&gt;working with faculty&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/office-hours/&#34;&gt;what office hours are for&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/writing/&#34;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; and conducting &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/literature-reviews/&#34;&gt;literature reviews&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/students/exams/&#34;&gt;studying for my exams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Advising For, Anyway?</title>
      <link>/resources/students/advising-role/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/advising-role/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Advising is a critical part of the undergraduate experience here at Saint Louis University. Like &lt;a href=&#34;/resources/letters&#34;&gt;letters of recommendation&lt;/a&gt;, I find that students are often unsure of how best to utilize and prepare for advising meetings. This post is meant to provide guidance specifically to my advisees, but is generally reflective of priorities that the Sociology and Computational Geospatial Science programs have in terms of advising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-advisers-one-goal&#34;&gt;Two Advisers, One Goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every student at SLU should have &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; advisers, an academic adviser in the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS), or in their home college, and a faculty mentor. You are strongly encouraged to meet with both your academic adviser and your faculty mentor on a regular basis since they serve slightly different functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The academic adviser is best positioned to make sure you are on pace to graduate and to help you navigate the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slu.edu/arts-and-sciences/student-resources/core-curriculum/core-requirements.php&#34;&gt;core curriculum requirements&lt;/a&gt;. As your faculty mentor, I have a &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; sense of the core curriculum requirements but will send you to your academic advisers for specific questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My role, in contrast, is to provide you with specific guidance on how to complete your major or minor in Sociology or Computation Geospatial Science. Faculty tend to know the specifics of program requirements and upcoming course offerings before CAS academic advisers do, and are also better positioned to provide advice on next steps after SLU like careers or graduate schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-role&#34;&gt;Your Role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advising is not a one-way relationship - like all relationships, both of us have a job to do. Your job is to be &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; engaged in your academic career. Please create and maintain a &lt;strong&gt;four year plan&lt;/strong&gt; that includes &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the courses you will need to take each semester to stay on course for graduation. The Sociology and Anthropology Department has created planning grids to help with this process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Sociology Major &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Sociology Major with Honors &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Sociology Minor &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; Computational Geospatial Science Minor &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#39;t have to use these worksheets, but they can be helpful for getting started. Many of my students create a digital version of these grids in Microsoft Excel or Apple Numbers. However you create your four year plan, you need one and you need to keep it updated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-to-come-see-me&#34;&gt;When to Come See Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I am your academic adviser, you should see me &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; twice per year. I send out mass emails prior to course registration asking you to signup for an advising slot. If you don&#39;t have much to talk about, sign up for a single 15 minute slot. If you have a lot to chat about, sign up for two or even three contiguous 15 minute slots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because these are my two regular advising periods does not mean I am otherwise unavailable. Feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:chris.prener@slu.edu&#34;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; to set-up a time to talk. I am &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; happy to meet with my advisees to check-in or provide guidance in between course registration advising sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-ready-for-our-meeting&#34;&gt;Getting Ready for Our Meeting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you come in for your advising meeting, update your &lt;strong&gt;four year plan&lt;/strong&gt;. Make sure you have a good sense of what requirements you have completed and what courses you still need to take. If you are coming in for a pre-registration meeting, take a look at Banner and browse through the courses that are available. You can also stop by the Sociology and Anthropology Department to pick up an updated list of courses available for the next semester. Please come to your meeting with some ideas about what courses you&#39;d like to take for the upcoming semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are meeting with me during the &lt;strong&gt;spring&lt;/strong&gt; of your &lt;strong&gt;junior year&lt;/strong&gt;, you will need to bring a form from your CAS adviser that lets them know what you still need to complete for your major or minor. If you don&#39;t bring it, you will have to come back later and have me sign the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-expect-during-our-meeting&#34;&gt;What to Expect During Our Meeting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we meet, I&#39;ll go through a copy of the appropriate degree checklist and four year plan (see &amp;ldquo;Your Role&amp;rdquo; above) and make sure you&#39;re making forward progress towards completing your major or minor. I&#39;ll also check in about any plans you might have for summer internships, research experience, jobs, and/or graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-do-after-we-meet&#34;&gt;What to Do After We Meet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need forms or petitions signed, please make sure you follow-up with me. Please also pay attention to registration dates and register for courses as soon as possible to ensure that you get seats in the courses that you need to be in. I am typically unable to help if a course fills up, so please make sure you have all holds removed and are able to register on-time for courses. Once you are registered, stay in touch and let me know if any issues arise. Otherwise, plan to update your &lt;strong&gt;four year plan&lt;/strong&gt; with your registered courses and start planning for the next semester!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing the Little Things Right</title>
      <link>/resources/students/little-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/little-things/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Settling into college can be daunting - there are a host of new relationships to navigate (roommates, advisers, faculty) and a whole new set of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_norm&#34;&gt;social and cultural norms&lt;/a&gt; to follow and occasionally break. Below are some tips for surviving in this brave new world you&#39;ve found yourself in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-call-us&#34;&gt;What to Call Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re coming from high school, you&#39;re probably used to calling your teachers &amp;ldquo;Mrs.&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Mr.&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Miss.&amp;quot;. This is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the approach you should take with professors. Universities have an elaborate [division of labor]https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_of_labour), and faculty often (but not always) have doctorates. The honorifics we use reflect this, and you want to make sure you get this right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always, always, always call faculty you haven&#39;t met before &amp;ldquo;Doctor&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Professor.&amp;rdquo; If you&#39;re not sure if your professor has a doctorate or not, feel free to use &amp;ldquo;Professor.&amp;rdquo; Better to over-assume their credentials and have them correct you than the opposite. If  you&#39;re cold calling or emailing someone, assume that they prefer to use &amp;ldquo;Doctor&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Professor.&amp;rdquo; The same is true if faculty do not tell you what to call them on the first day of class - it is better to be overly polite than it is to take an informal approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can look for clues in how we sign our emails. If a professor signs with their first name, this is typically invitation to respond using their first name as well. If a professor signs their emails with initials, it&#39;s best to stick with &amp;ldquo;Doctor&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Professor&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;Dr.&amp;rdquo; / &amp;ldquo;Prof&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some professors are OK with students using their first name (I let my students call me Chris, for example). However, even if a professor says it is OK to use their first name, it is also totally fine to continue to use honorifics with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can all seem a bit petty, but it&#39;s an important exercise in acknowledging the division of labor you&#39;re a part of. This is especially true for faculty from groups typically underrepresented in academia (women in many disciplines, and faculty from racial and ethnic minority groups). Their expertise is unfortunately questioned or ignored, and using honorifics signals acknowledges that expertise in a small but meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing-emails&#34;&gt;Writing Emails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the interactions you&#39;ll have with faculty are going to be over email, so it is worth taking just a bit of time to put some thought into how you do that. First, always use your university email account. This will clearly identify who you are in a way that a gmail account may not (&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:skibum02@gmail.com&#34;&gt;skibum02@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, for example). Second, when you start the email, make sure you get the honorific right (see above) and make sure you spell our names correctly. Beyond that, I love the tips in &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@lportwoodstacer/how-to-email-your-professor-without-being-annoying-af-cf64ae0e4087&#34;&gt;this fantastic medium post&lt;/a&gt; for putting together an effective email to professors (or really anyone) - follow them all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we&#39;re on the subject, it is also important to remember that this is the way the University and faculty are going to communicate with you. You need to check your email daily!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;show-us-the-love&#34;&gt;Show Us the Love&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re humans, too (I swear), and that means we have egos, sensitivities, and even feelings from time to time. While deep down we know that you have multiple priorities and our class may not always be at the top of your list, you also don&#39;t need to rub it in. In particular, you want to avoid telegraphing to professors that you are only taking the class for a requirement, or because it doesn&#39;t meet on Fridays (a game I played in college). There are some professors who might be OK with hearing this, but I&#39;d say we&#39;re in the minority and it is better to assume that it won&#39;t be taken well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;remember-there-are-many-of-you&#34;&gt;Remember There Are Many of You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of you will have somewhere between four and six professors each semester. In contrast, I typically have 50-100 students in a given semester here at SLU. I find that students often either (a) forgot that this imbalance exists or (b) assume that because this imbalance exists, we don&#39;t have time. Nothing could be further from the truth - we&#39;ll always make time for your email or meeting, but just need you to remember the imbalance and be patient with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that students often don&#39;t understand is that teaching is only part of our job. We also are expected to be actively engaged with research and writing during the semester, and be involved with what we call service (typically helping our Department, College, or discipline run). Again, this doesn&#39;t mean that we aren&#39;t able to help or don&#39;t want to help, but that we may not be at our desk every day or have availability certain times of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-through-but-admit-when-you-cant&#34;&gt;Follow Through, But Admit When You Can&#39;t&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part of showing us the love is following through. If you say you&#39;re going to come to office hours, come! If you volunteer to help with some research, make sure you fulfill your end of the arrangement you make with us. If you cannot follow through, a quick email saying something came up goes a long way. Students sometimes drop off the radar, and its much better to be upfront with us about whatever change or challenge has come up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;keep-yourself-organized&#34;&gt;Keep Yourself Organized&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time management is a skill that I see a lot of students struggle with (and that I struggled with in college). &lt;a href=&#34;https://students.dartmouth.edu/academic-skills/learning-resources/time-management-&#34;&gt;Dartmouth&lt;/a&gt; has a great set of resources for managing yourself, getting and staying organized, and using a calendar. This is especially important because most professors will tell you that they&#39;re going to treat you like an adult - our job isn&#39;t to nag you, make you come to class, or check in constantly. This is a bit different than the role that teachers in high school fulfill. If you decide you don&#39;t want to do an assignment, or come to class, ultimately we&#39;ll let you make those decisions and we&#39;ll expect you to understand that there may be consequences (typically in the form of grades that cannot be revised or changed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, keeping yourself organized is critical to being successful! Whatever you do does not need to be elaborate or technologically sophisticated - a pad that you use to write down what you need to accomplish each day and a simple calendar can be enough. The importat thing is to start early with good organization habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;communicate-ahead-of-time&#34;&gt;Communicate Ahead of Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest mistakes students make is that they wait until it is too late to ask for help or extensions. Almost all the faculty I know, including myself, would rather have these discussions as soon as you know there is an issue. I will bend over backwards to help students if I can, but I also need to know that there is a need out there that needs to be addressed. This is particularly important because of what I said above about there being many of you - sometimes we need a day or two to follow-up, and so communicating ahead of time helps us help you just a bit more effectively and efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;take-care-of-yourself&#34;&gt;Take Care of Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many of you, this is your first time out on your own. We&#39;re all going to treat you like an adult. When we say that in this context, we mean that if you want to stay up all night, only eat ice cream, and nap during the afternoon, we&#39;re not going to stand in your way. While it is fun to exercise some new forms of autonomy, it can also be easy to get sucked into habits that ultimately are destructive. Similarly, it can be easy to float or disengage from things like school work. While you should absolutely have fun, cut loose, and enjoy being out on your own, you should also start working now on self care and stress management. You will need these skills to be successful here, and you will have a lot more fun if you are not constantly under the burdens of stress, anxiety, or depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ask-for-help&#34;&gt;Ask for Help&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you aren&#39;t sure exactly how to deal with stress, depression, anxiety, or another problem, please ask us for help (we&#39;ve been there, trust me). If you need immediate help, SLU&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slu.edu/life-at-slu/university-counseling/index.php&#34;&gt;University Counseling Center&lt;/a&gt; can be reached at 314-977-TALK. There are also a host of resources both &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slu.edu/life-at-slu/university-counseling/crisis-resources.php&#34;&gt;within SLU and outside of SLU&lt;/a&gt; that are at your disposal. If whatever is going on in your life is going to impact your school work, you also need to talk to your professors. You don&#39;t need to give us all the details, but we need to at least know that you&#39;re facing some challenges. We may have to check in with the University about some of this, so know that what you tell us may not be able to be kept just between us. But please, if you find yourself underwater or struggling, ask &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; for help. We want you to be happy and successful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internships</title>
      <link>/resources/students/internships/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/internships/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Internships are a critical way to build skills whether you are headed to graduate school or to a job after you graduate from SLU. Internships are something that I advise &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my students to do if they can, though I recognize that unpaid internships and those that require owning a car can pose a barrier for some. Several of my students have been successful at identifying internships on-campus, which can be a great option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note that I typically supervise internships only for students who are assigned to me for advising. If you are a Sociology or GIS student who is not my advisee, please speak to your mentor in the Department first.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;identifying-internships&#34;&gt;Identifying Internships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a myraid of options when it comes to internships, which means finding the right opportunity will take some leg work. Start &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt; in advanced of when you want an internship experience. Some resources include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SLU&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slu.edu/life-at-slu/career-services/index.php&#34;&gt;Career Services Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SLU&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://slu.joinhandshake.com/login&#34;&gt;Handshake&lt;/a&gt; database of jobs and internships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;many State of Missouri agencies have dedicated internship pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/&#34;&gt;National Science Foundation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/crssprgm/reu/reu_search.jsp&#34;&gt;Research Experience for Undergraduate Programs&lt;/a&gt; - university research summer programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAJOBS &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usajobs.gov/Help/working-in-government/unique-hiring-paths/students/&#34;&gt;Student and Recent Graduate site&lt;/a&gt; - for opportunities at a federal agency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some specific programs for students with technical and/or GIS skills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codeforamerica.org&#34;&gt;Code for America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ESRI&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.esri.com/en-us/about/careers/student-jobs&#34;&gt;Student Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The National Geospatial Intelligence Agency&#39;s (NGA) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nga.mil/CAREERS/STUDENTOPP/Pages/default.aspx&#34;&gt;Student Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are a few local public health related summer programs as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Casa De Salud, a SLU affiliated primary care clinic, has regular &lt;a href=&#34;https://casadesaludstl.org/volunteers/non-licensed-volunteers/&#34;&gt;internship and volunteer opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Washington University in St. Louis Institute for Public Health&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://publichealth.wustl.edu/institute-for-public-health-summer-research-program-public-and-global-health/&#34;&gt;Summer Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-credit&#34;&gt;For Credit?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to take internships for credit as part of your Sociology major as long as you are enrolled in a credit-bearing course &lt;em&gt;in the same semester&lt;/em&gt; that you complete the internship. You can take a variable number of credit hours (1 or more). Internship policies are set by the College of Arts and Sciences and are available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slu.edu/arts-and-sciences/student-resources/policies-procedures.php&#34;&gt;on their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not, however, required to complete internships for credit. Some of my students opt to do internships for the skills and experience alone, especially if internships are completed during the summer. The choice is yours, and I&#39;m happy to meet with you to discuss your options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;internship-expectations&#34;&gt;Internship Expectations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the policies governing internships are set by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slu.edu/arts-and-sciences/student-resources/policies-procedures.php&#34;&gt;College of Arts and Sciences&lt;/a&gt;. Once you identify a possible internship site, discuss it with me to make sure it is suitable. Typically, I&#39;ll ask you to keep a journal during your internship and use it as a basis for a 7-10 page paper that connects your internship work and organiation to what you&#39;ve been learning in your sociology courses. These requirements are determined on a case-by-case basis, however, and are subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Office Hours are Really Student Hours</title>
      <link>/resources/students/office-hours/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/office-hours/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my experience, we don&#39;t do a great job communicating to students about what office hours are for and when you should come to them. So, if you&#39;ve had questions about what office hours are or when to come, you are not alone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-office-hours-are&#34;&gt;What Office Hours Are&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll start with what I think we (professors) think is obvious but in practice is not always - office hours are &lt;strong&gt;for you&lt;/strong&gt;! This is time we reserve each week for students to drop by, get help, or just catch up. I may spend the time doing work if I&#39;m not meeting with students, but its work I am happy (and able) to stop if you want to chat. So, if you come to my office (or to the lab where I sometimes hold office hours), you are definitely not interrupting. In fact, I&#39;d &lt;strong&gt;rather&lt;/strong&gt; talk to you then do work. Getting to know students is part of my job, and one that I particularly enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-to-come&#34;&gt;When to Come&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most students are not a weekly presence at office hours, so the next real question is when you should come. To some degree this depends on your goal. If you want to stop by and talk about a specific assignment or grade, it helps to come as soon as you&#39;ve received your grade. If you want to talk about &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;studying for tests&lt;/a&gt;, try to come a couple of weeks before an exam rather than right before it - that will give you time to alter any study practices based on our conversation. The same is true if you want to proactively address an assignment - don&#39;t come right before it is due, but rather a couple weeks out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;its-ok-to-just-chat&#34;&gt;It&#39;s OK to Just Chat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#39;t need an excuse to come to office hours beyond wanting to talk, though. Getting to know faculty is important, even when you are a first year student. We can help you pick classes, think about study abroad, find internships, or just talk about survival strategies if that is what you need. You&#39;ll also need us for some of those things - letters of recommendation are sometimes needed for study abroad, and often needed for things like internships, graduate school, and medical school. It is much, much harder to write letters that are convincing and compelling if you don&#39;t know the student well, and &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;I may say no to students if I don&#39;t know them outside of the classroom&lt;/a&gt;. Lay the foundation for this early - come back and check in - you don&#39;t need to stay long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;they-arent-just-for-current-students&#34;&gt;They Aren&#39;t Just for Current Students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also don&#39;t have to be in a class with me that semester to come by - I love catching up with students from previous semesters. Come back and tell me how your semester abroad, your summer touring with the Dead, or your sweet data science internship turned out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So You Need a Letter of Recommendation</title>
      <link>/resources/students/letters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/letters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Letters of recommendation, or references more generally, are an important part of many internship, job, and graduate school applications. As faculty, we get requests every semester from students to (ideally) sing their praises. So, we expect you to ask! However, I&#39;ve found that students are sometimes unsure both &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; to ask and &lt;em&gt;how to ask&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-to-ask&#34;&gt;Who to Ask&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask professors who know you well and will have a lot to say about you.&lt;/strong&gt; For me, this means I&#39;ve been able to get to know you outside of class. If you&#39;ve never spoken up in class, come to office hours, or otherwise had some kind of interaction with me, it is nearly impossible for me to write a convincing, comprehensive letter of recommendation. This means you need to &lt;em&gt;think ahead&lt;/em&gt;! Don&#39;t wait until you need a letter from me to swing by my office - start building that relationship well ahead of time so that, when it comes time to ask for the favor of a letter (and it will come time!), I am able to enthusiastically say &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Letters are easiest to write for students who I have had in more than one class. So, if you&#39;ve only known me briefly and in a limited way, you should consider asking a faculty member who knows you better. Similarly, if you did not do well in the only class you&#39;ve had with me, you are better off asking another faculty member who can speak to your strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another &amp;ldquo;trick&amp;rdquo; is to think of faculty as being specialists. I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; write a letter of recommendation on your behalf for admission to a doctoral program in chemistry, but do you really want me to? My letter will not carry the weight that a letter would from a faculty member in chemistry or an allied discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The questions I suggest students ask themselves before approaching faculty are therefore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well does the professor know me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which of my strengths can they speak to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can they uniquely speak to something related to this job/internship/graduate school application?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you aren&#39;t sure if I am the best fit or not, swing by my office to ask! I&#39;m happy to entertain informal requests and talk with you about the letter writing process ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-ask&#34;&gt;How to Ask&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, &lt;strong&gt;ask&lt;/strong&gt;! Nothing is more frustrating with this process than being cold-called by a colleague, an HR staff member, or by a supervisor asking for a recommendation that I am not prepared to give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you ask, &lt;strong&gt;ask well ahead of time&lt;/strong&gt;. This is less important if I am only serving as a reference and will not be required to write a letter on your behalf. I need, typically, at least &lt;strong&gt;two weeks notice&lt;/strong&gt; before a submission deadline for a student who I have not written a letter for previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you approach me, make sure you &lt;strong&gt;have everything I will need&lt;/strong&gt; in hand. This means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a description of the position you are applying for,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a few ideas of things you want me to emphasize in my letter,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an updated resume,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and instructions on how I should submit your letter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are asking me to provide letters for more than one or two jobs, internships, or schools, please also provide a &lt;strong&gt;Google sheet&lt;/strong&gt; that breaks down each position by deadline so that I can make sure all of the letters get to their destinations on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have all of your materials together, please &lt;strong&gt;come see me in person&lt;/strong&gt; instead of just emailing me. This will allow me the chance to ask you questions about the position and make sure I have everything that I need to write the best letter possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;if-i-say-no&#34;&gt;If I Say &amp;lsquo;No&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please be forewarned that &lt;strong&gt;I might say &amp;lsquo;no&amp;rsquo; to a request&lt;/strong&gt; if I do not feel like I can write you a positive or comprehensive letter. This may be because you have not done well in my classes, or because I don&#39;t know you well outside of class. This is particularly true for my larger classes like Introduction to Sociology, where I do not get a chance to know many students outside of the classroom. This goes back to my earlier advice - make sure you are asking faculty who know you well and who can speak to your strengths! I also might say &amp;lsquo;no&amp;rsquo; if I am not given sufficient lead time, so please heed my advice about asking for a letter early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I say &amp;lsquo;no&amp;rsquo;, please do not take it personally. I get multiple requests for recommendations and letters each semester, and I need to prioritize students that I am best positioned to write about. If I don&#39;t feel like that is you, I&#39;ll be more than happy to help you brainstorm about who might be best to ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;following-up&#34;&gt;Following Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&#39;ve asked, and I&#39;ve said &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;, &lt;strong&gt;please follow-up as deadlines approach&lt;/strong&gt;. I do my best to get letters in before deadlines, and will reach out as I submit letters on your behalf to let you know about my progress. However, it is in your best interest to reach out if you have not heard from me and a deadline is approaching. Please don&#39;t feel shy about reaching out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if you get one of the positions I&#39;ve written a letter for, &lt;strong&gt;let me know&lt;/strong&gt;! It is always gratifying to hear about your successes, so please reach out with the good news!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for Writing in the Social Sciences</title>
      <link>/resources/students/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have writing assignments in all of my classes (even my methods classes), and there are definitely patterns for where students get things right and wrong when it comes to writing assignments. Here are a couple of tips for maximizing your rate of success when it comes to social science writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;make-a-plan&#34;&gt;Make a Plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write an outline - it can just be a few bullet points on a sheet of paper to start. Particularly for students coming from the world of lab sciences, where lab notes have structure to them, even a short writing assignment where you open up a blank document can be daunting. So don&#39;t open up that blank document without a plan! Start with bullet points, then add in main ideas and supporting evidence. Work yourself towards a paragraph by paragraph or (for longer assignments) a section by section plan for approaching writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;include-a-road-map-in-your-intro&#34;&gt;Include a Road-map in Your Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introductions are hard to write, and some folks recommend that you write it at the end so that you can convincingly lay out what you actually did (as opposed to what you thought you&#39;d do but didn&#39;t end up doing). No matter when you write it, make sure you have a clear road-map for your paper - tell your audience (so, me!) what you intend to &lt;strong&gt;show&lt;/strong&gt; in your paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-an-argument&#34;&gt;Have An Argument&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another place introductions go awry is that they don&#39;t actually take a stand. What is the &lt;strong&gt;point&lt;/strong&gt; of your paper? What are you trying to illustrate or convince your audience (so, me!) of?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-avoid-hyperbole&#34;&gt;But Avoid Hyperbole&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, having an over-the-top argument is just as bad. It is a good idea to avoid saying things like &amp;ldquo;the most severe problem in America&amp;rdquo; because I will inevitably write back that this might not actually be the case. You want to be a bit circumspect with your language without being unclear - this is a practice that takes time to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;be-succinct-and-organized&#34;&gt;Be Succinct and Organized&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One common thing I see with undergraduate writing is that it can&amp;hellip; ramble. I think that having a plan (see above) can help address this to some degree. One way to avoid this is to make sure you&#39;re aggressively using paragraph breaks. Your paragraph should not run for a full page, and your sentences need to be well organized, too (none of us are &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stream_of_consciousness&#34;&gt;William Faulkner&lt;/a&gt;, right?!). You want each paragraph to have a point, and want to make sure it is working in the service of your larger argument. Your paragraphs need to &lt;strong&gt;flow&lt;/strong&gt; from one to the other (we call these &amp;ldquo;transitions&amp;rdquo;), and writing good transitions is &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;avoid-contractions&#34;&gt;Avoid Contractions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most common pieces of feedback I give, aside from the need for more paragraph breaks, is to write out &amp;ldquo;do not&amp;rdquo; instead of saying &amp;ldquo;don&#39;t.&amp;rdquo; Why? Using contractions can convey an informal sense to your readers, and you want to avoid doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learn-grammar-rules&#34;&gt;Learn Grammar Rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, make sure you&#39;re comfortable with &amp;ldquo;their&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;their&amp;rdquo; (but don&#39;t worry about &amp;ldquo;they&#39;re&amp;rdquo;, because you&#39;re avoiding contractions, right?). Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.grammarly.com/blog/30-grammar-mistakes-writers-should-avoid/&#34;&gt;great rundown&lt;/a&gt; of some common grammar mistakes to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;write-actively&#34;&gt;Write Actively&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professors strongly dislike &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.grammarly.com/blog/passive-voice/&#34;&gt;writing that uses passive voice&lt;/a&gt;. Make sure you work on spotting it in your own work and writing your papers in an active voice as much as you can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dont-do-it-the-night-before&#34;&gt;Don&#39;t Do It The Night Before&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give yourself time to proofread. Perhaps the night before is sufficient for this if you can come back to it in the morning, but the more time you give yourself for this, the better. I&#39;ll even look at work if I&#39;ve got enough lead time (at least a week in advance of the due date).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find you struggle with clarity, reading your work out loud can be really helpful. Its awkward, of course, so do it in a space where you&#39;re alone (the library probably isn&#39;t an ideal place for this exercise). Another strategy that I use for my own work is to use a tool like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.grammarly.com&#34;&gt;Grammarly&lt;/a&gt;. It has helped me improve my writing, and I&#39;m an enthusiastic supporter of the platform!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reward-yourself&#34;&gt;Reward Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing is hard, and it doesn&#39;t happen all at once. This is another reason not to start the night before. Have a breakthrough or finish a hard section? Go celebrate! Get it all submitted? Celebrate some more! You worked hard and deserve a chance to give yourself a high five or a pint of ice cream. Or both.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Short Guide to Conducting Literature Reviews</title>
      <link>/resources/students/literature-reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/literature-reviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Literature reviews are a common assignment, but all too often we take it for granted that students know how to find, digest, and document academic sources related to whatever topic they&#39;ve identified.  When a professor asks you for a literature review, they are asking you to systematically search for and review &lt;a href=&#34;https://library.sdsu.edu/research-services/research-help/peer-reviewed-articles&#34;&gt;peer reviewed&lt;/a&gt; literature on your topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-peer-review&#34;&gt;What is peer review?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are interested primarily in the peer reviewed literature because we we want to understand the scholarly debate that has unfolded about our topic. The peer review process is also one indicator of quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We typically think of peer review as falling into two categories - books and journal articles. While the process for reviewing books is different from articles, academic books are typically sent out for review before they are published by the publisher. Peer reviewed books are typically published by either a university press (e.g. Oxford University Press or The University of California Press) or by a publishing house that specializes in academic content (e.g. John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journal articles that are peer reviewed will be published in an academic journal. There are &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;many journals that publish sociological content&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, along with others that publish more broadly in the social sciences (&lt;em&gt;Social Science &amp;amp; Medicine&lt;/em&gt; is a great example). Beaware that not all journals are created equal - there is a whole group of so-called &amp;ldquo;predatory&amp;rdquo; journals (along with &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;fake conferences&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;) that &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;capitalize on the &amp;ldquo;publish or perish&amp;rdquo; culture of academia&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; as well as the relative isolation of many scholars in developing countries. While there are some lists of &amp;ldquo;predatory&amp;rdquo; journals, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;learning how to evaluate &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; articles critically&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; is perhaps the best way to protect yourself against citing poor research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conducting-the-literature-search&#34;&gt;Conducting the Literature Search&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;analysis-development&#34;&gt;Analysis Development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With your research question in-hand, you will want to follow a semi-structured process for identifying appropriate peer reviewed sources. Document the places you search and the search terms / key words you use in your research log. As you find sources, I recommend keeping track of them in a spreadsheet. This makes it easier to figure out if you have already found and downloaded an article that you may come across multiple times. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Dr. Raul Pacheco-Vega&#39;s website&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; has a great example of a spreadsheet used for tracking literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sheet of a spreadsheet workbook, keep track of the sources you&#39;ve found, scanned (see &amp;ldquo;[Evaluating Sources]&amp;quot;), and found not to be useful. This is to serve as a reference later if you come across an article again and cannot remember if you already looked at it or not. You can easily generate bibliographic citations in Google Scholar by searching for the source and clicking the double quote icon under its Google Scholar entry (highlighted in red):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/googleScholar1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking that icon should open a pop-up window that includes pre-formatted references in a number of different styles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/googleScholar2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to use Chicago, which requires minimal editing for both books and articles to convert the citation to ASA (see &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;#writing-an-annotated-bibliography&#34;&gt;Writing an Annotated Bibliography&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; for an explanation about why ASA is used). For books, you&#39;ll want to move the year so that is referenced after the author&#39;s name and add the city and state before the publisher&#39;s name. For articles, you&#39;ll want to move the year and simplify the volume and issue numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For sources that you find useful, enter them into a second sheet that includes a citation as well as how you found the article, what the major themes are, any notes you think you need on high-level details about the paper, and cross-references that indicate if the paper is cited by other papers you&#39;ve found. These cross-references are important for making linkages between different aspects of the literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;process&#34;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly encourage students to follow this general process for identifying appropriate literature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify appropriate search terms:&lt;/strong&gt; Based on your research question, what are the keywords that might help you find relevant articles?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify the &amp;ldquo;state of the art&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/strong&gt; Start by searching Annual Review journals (or similar, such as Sociology Compass) for recent articles that summarize the state of the literature in your area. You may not find an exact match, but you may find reviews of related topics. Use these articles to get a sense of what the &amp;ldquo;state of the art&amp;rdquo; is for your topic area(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citations from review articles:&lt;/strong&gt; Use the review articles you find to identify both seminal publications that define a field of study (may not be recent) as well as more recent empirical studies. Find and download these articles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search other social science publications:&lt;/strong&gt; Whether or not you find helpful review articles, you will want to also search other key journals. Start with generalist journals and then move to more specific journals focused on particular types of research. Use the same search terms described above. In sociology, for example, the major generalist journals are &lt;em&gt;American Sociological Review&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Sociology&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Social Forces&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Social Problems&lt;/em&gt;. In one of my sub-fields, medical sociology, &lt;em&gt;Social Science and Medicine&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Journal of Health and Social Behavior&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Health and Place&lt;/em&gt; are all key journals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search related journals:&lt;/strong&gt; Are there journals from other disciplines that are related? If so, search those as well using your search terms. In my research, the &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Public Health&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Annals of the American Association of Geographers&lt;/em&gt; are both important journals from related disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search &lt;em&gt;Sociological Abstracts&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; If you are not finding many citations, you may want to search the Sociological Abstracts database, which catalogs many more sociological journals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iterative Processing of Articles:&lt;/strong&gt; As you read through the articles you find and download in steps 3 through 7, seek out the studies that they cite that seem related. Download them, read them, and identify more related studies that they cite, then start the process over. Also use this process to identify books. Google Scholar can be instrumental in providing listings of articles that cite a given source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are coming from outside sociology and working on a project that is rooted in your home discipline, you will have to alter the above process to match the key &lt;em&gt;Annual Review&lt;/em&gt; journal or journals as well as the other major publication outlets in your field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;evaluating-sources&#34;&gt;Evaluating Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, make sure what you&#39;ve found is &lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-peer-review&#34;&gt;peer reviewed&lt;/a&gt;. If you&#39;ve found a report or a popular press article (something like Time Magazine), hang onto it if you think it provides helpful contextual background but it should not be part of your literature search. If you&#39;ve identified a dissertation or a thesis that seems helpful, there are typically two things worth doing: (1) check to see if it has been published as an article or a book (sometimes you&#39;ll have to check out the author&#39;s CV if you can find it), and (2) use it to identify other peer reviewed materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Science Magazine&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; has a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;great article&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; that describes how different academics read articles. If you look through their responses, you&#39;ll notice that few take a new article, read the abstract than read through the article cover to cover. Instead there are a variety of approaches to finding out the &amp;ldquo;meat&amp;rdquo; of the article quickly, without reading it in its entirety. Use this as a strategy for figuring out whether or not an article is a good fit for your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the abstract, introduction, and discussion/conclusion sections to get a sense of the paper. Ask yourself if it makes a contribution to what you are researching. If it does, add it to your spreadsheet and fill out the necessary details. If it &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt;, add it to the &amp;ldquo;discard&amp;rdquo; list so you can find it later if you change your mind (or if you forget whether you&#39;ve read it or not!). You can find some more details on the &amp;ldquo;AIC&amp;rdquo; technique for reading on &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Dr. Raul Pacheco-Vega&#39;s website&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;. He also has a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;reading strategies&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the article does fit into your research, take some basic &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;synthetic notes&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; about the article. These will form the basis of your paragraphs for each source in the annotated bibliography. I find the [SQ3R method] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQ3R&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQ3R&lt;/a&gt;) to be a particularly effective note taking strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing-an-annotated-bibliography&#34;&gt;Writing an Annotated Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The annotated bibliography itself is a document that lists your sources in alphabetical order (or alphabetized within groupings for specific categories). Begin each entry with a full, properly formatted citation using the &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;American Sociological Association (ASA) citation style&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often get questions about whether students can use alternate citation formats. Different journals use different formats, so it is not possible for academics to learn and become comfortable with &lt;em&gt;just one&lt;/em&gt; citation style. Rather, we use multiple citation styles regularly. Often, an article manuscript will be written in a specific citation style for one journal only to have to be reformatted in a different style for another journal if it is rejected on the first submission. Learning new citation styles quickly is therefore an important lesson, and one reason why ASA is the only citation style I accept for this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the citation style, there should be one to two paragraphs summarizing the article and its importance for your project. The strongest annotated bibliographies will draw substantive or thematic connections between sources, noting which articles are cited by others and which articles share important connections. This will help you develop the synthesis your literature review section for the paper requires. For more, see Dr. Raul Pacheco-Vega&#39;s post on &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;writing an annotated bibliography&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-resources&#34;&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;websites&#34;&gt;Websites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pitt.libguides.com/literaturereview&#34;&gt;University of Pittsburgh Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://libguides.library.kent.edu/litreview&#34;&gt;Kent State University Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://guides.library.illinois.edu/lit&#34;&gt;University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://libguides.bc.edu/litreview&#34;&gt;Boston College Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://libguides.utoledo.edu/litreview/home&#34;&gt;University of Toledo Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;books-in-piuss-collection&#34;&gt;Books in Pius&#39;s Collection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aveyard, H. (2014). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b4026794&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;Doing a literature review in health and social care: A practical guide&lt;/a&gt; (3rd ed.). Maidenhead: Open University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coughlan, M., Cronin, P., &amp;amp; Ryan, F. (2013). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b3600877&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;Doing a literature review in nursing, health and social care&lt;/a&gt;. Los Angeles: Sage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ridley, D. (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b3401752&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;The literature review: A step-by-step guide for students&lt;/a&gt; (2nd ed.). London: Sage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver, P. (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b4135303&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;Succeeding with your literature review: A handbook for students&lt;/a&gt;.  Berkshire, England: McGraw-Hill: Open University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bettany-Saltikov, J. (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b4058001&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;How to do a systematic literature review in nursing: A step-by-step guide&lt;/a&gt;. Maidenhead, Berkshire, England: McGraw Hill Open University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Booth, A., Papaioannou, D., &amp;amp; Sutton, A. (2012). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b3400237&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;Systematic approaches to a successful literature review&lt;/a&gt;. London; Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machi, L.A. (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezp.slu.edu/login?url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=cat00825a&amp;amp;AN=slu.b3008587&amp;amp;site=eds-live&#34;&gt;The literature review: Six steps to success&lt;/a&gt;. Thousand Oaks, CA: Corwin Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for Studying for Exams</title>
      <link>/resources/students/exams/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/resources/students/exams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I get a lot of questions, particularly from first year students, about the best ways to study for my exams. Here are some general thoughts on maximizing your changes for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-everything-together&#34;&gt;Get Everything Together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I give advice, I assume that students have been taking notes on the readings, lectures, and documentaries. I think this is the single best things you can do to maximize your chances for success on my exams. When it is time to start studying, I recommend &lt;em&gt;synthesizing&lt;/em&gt; everything. That is, taking all of your notes on a particular topic (like &amp;ldquo;Culture&amp;rdquo;) and combining them together into a single study guide for each major heading on the syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on major headings and keywords from chapters and lectures, as well as the names that show up in readings and during class. The highest probability questions come from topics that appear in both the readings and the lectures, though I&#39;ll pull a few questions from the lectures that weren&#39;t part of a reading and vice versa. I tend to create exams that provide pretty even coverage of the lectures within each section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-focus-on&#34;&gt;Things to Focus On&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My exams combine two question types - multiple choice and short answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;studying-for-multiple-choice-questions&#34;&gt;Studying for Multiple Choice Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple choice questions tend to revolve around demonstrating that you know the definition of key terms or can reverse the process and identify a key term if given the definition. I sometimes test names of important sociologists directly - &amp;ldquo;which classical theorist is associated with theories related to organizations and bureaucracy?&amp;rdquo; (A: Weber). Other times I use the name as a hint or a clue regarding the correct answer. Other times I test both of these things by providing a scenario - &amp;ldquo;this particular person has been in the news - their leadership style is best represented by which of these Weberian ideal-types?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to make sure you know, therefore, the main ideas expressed in each major topic of the course, the people that go along with them, the social theories we discuss, and the substance of really critical pieces of evidence (I might ask, for example, about the essential details from a documentary, case study, or illustrative example we&#39;ve discussed in class). Often, questions related to this final point are pretty general and if you read between the lines, you can zero in on the correct answer if you think about the major themes at play even if you can&#39;t remember the specific example the question asks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;studying-for-short-answer-questions&#34;&gt;Studying for Short Answer Questions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Big Questions&amp;rdquo; on the lecture notes are good fodder for studying. You&#39;ll be given an example of something, like a picture, plot, map, or just a short description of some social phenomenon, and be asked to connect it to what we&#39;ve been talking about. These tend to focus on a specific week or lecture, but the best answers will pull information in from the class as a whole. The more specifics you can give, in terms of defining terms and fully exploring the idea in the prompt, the stronger your answer will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-course-docs-fit-in&#34;&gt;How do Course Docs fit in?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the Fall 2019 semester, I&#39;ve begun posting what I call &lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-soc1120.github.io/docs/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Course Docs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. These are experimental, and will not necessarily be available for all weeks of my intro course. The intent of these is not to re-hash or cover course material, but rather to take you &lt;em&gt;further&lt;/em&gt; if you &lt;em&gt;want to learn more&lt;/em&gt;. This means I &lt;strong&gt;will not be directly testing&lt;/strong&gt; the content of these pages. However, reading through them and using them as a jumping off point will help you learn the course material in a more thorough way. You should absolutely be able to be successful without them, of course, but you will be more confident in your mastery of the course material itself with them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
