<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GIS | Christopher Prener</title>
    <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/tag/gis/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://chris-prener.github.io/tag/gis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>GIS</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2017-2021 Christopher G. Prener</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://chris-prener.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>GIS</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/tag/gis/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/covid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My interest in public-facing work has inspired an &lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/covid_daily_viz/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;eighteen-month public science project&lt;/a&gt; to compile and disseminate descriptive statistics about the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic in Missouri. You can view the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/MO_HEALTH_Covid_Tracking&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;data set creation code&lt;/a&gt; and data &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/covid_daily_viz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;vizualization code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a manuscript currently under review for &lt;em&gt;Contexts&lt;/em&gt;, I describe this as a variation on our discipline&amp;rsquo;s notion of &amp;ldquo;public sociology&amp;rdquo; - descriptive empirical work rooted in moving public discourse, rather than disciplinary knowledge, forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have leveraged these data with colleagues at all three major St. Louis universities and local community organizations for several publications and papers in progress. This work aims to understand variations in spatial and social factors associated with the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emergency Medical Services</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/ems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/ems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Emergency Medical Services (EMS) project is my original graduate research project. Begun in 2009 as a pilot study and expanded between 2011 and 2015 as my dissertation research, the project has aimed to understand the experience urban EMS work. My interest in the topic is rooted in my own experience as an Emergency Medical Technician. This research has culminated in a book manuscript, &lt;em&gt;Medicine at the Margins&lt;/em&gt;, which is under contract with Fordham University Press and undergoing minor revisions after peer review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the book, I argue that three types of marginality define EMS work: (1) the EMS system has a tenuous relationship with both the formal health care system and the broader first responder system, existing in a gray area between the two; (2) marginalized work conditions, which include 24-hour shifts filled with downtime spent fighting boredom, characterize EMS work; and (3) EMS work in practice is defined not by the most acute patients but those with chronic mental health issues, substance use disorders, and housing instability who live in particular neighborhoods within cities. Providers&#39; views of where these patients live, which I measure with qualitative GIS techniques, diverge from more objective measures of EMS work in this city. These findings allow me to provide empirical evidence of how neighborhood stigmas arise through work routines and institutional practices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geospatial and Computational Approaches</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/computational/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/computational/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the course of my substantive work, I have developed &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages to advance my research agenda. To accompany these software tools, I have written several papers describing their intellectual contributions. These include several discrete areas - geocoding and address normalization, interpolating population estimates, and qualitative GIS data collection and analysis. These papers emphasize the specific contributions of the specific software libraries and underscore a shared emphasis on reproducibility, open data, and decreasing barriers for everyone to participate in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My published packages include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;areal&lt;/code&gt; - Areal Weighted Interpolation (first released in December 2018) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=areal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/areal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/areal/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01221&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Publication&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;biscale&lt;/code&gt; - Tools and Palettes for Bivariate Thematic Mapping (first released in May 2019) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=biscale&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/biscale&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/biscale/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;censusxy&lt;/code&gt; - Access the U.S. Census Bureau Geocoder (first released in August 2019) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=censusxy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/censusxy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/censusxy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/tgis.12741&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Publication&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;compstatr&lt;/code&gt; - Tools for St. Louis Crime Data (first released in April 2019) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=compstatr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/compstatr&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/compstatr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;driftR&lt;/code&gt; - Drift Correcting Water Quality Data (first released in December 2017) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shaughnessyar/driftR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://shaughnessyar.github.io/driftR/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10661-019-7586-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Publication&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;qualmap&lt;/code&gt; - Opinionated Approach for Digitizing Semi-structured Qualitative GIS Data (first released in September 2018) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=qualmap&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/qualmap&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/qualmap/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;stlcsb&lt;/code&gt; - Managing St. Louis CSB Data (first released in February 2019) [&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=stlcsb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/slu-openGIS/stlcsb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;] [&lt;a href=&#34;https://slu-opengis.github.io/stlcsb/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Redlining, Segregation, and St. Louis</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/st-louis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/project/st-louis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This major project focuses on documenting the historical origins of neighborhood stigmas as well as their contemporary consequences. I use St. Louis as a case study, arguing in my &lt;em&gt;Sociology Compass&lt;/em&gt; article that urban sociology has systematically ignored cities in the literal and figurative American South. My work to date, published in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Urban Affairs&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Applied Geography&lt;/em&gt; as well as in several working papers, focuses on segregation, vacancy, violent crime, and poor health in the St. Louis region. Like &lt;a href=&#34;https://chris-prener.github.io/project/ems/&#34;&gt;my EMS work&lt;/a&gt;, I make extensive use of GIS techniques and am branching into machine learning with a computer science colleague as we look to general digital models of St. Louis neighborhoods lost to urban renewal efforts. These rely on processing historical maps and images, beginning with the former Mill Creek Valley neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This overarching focus is the centerpiece of my research effort moving forward. I am developing a book prospectus tentatively titled &lt;em&gt;Detrimental Influences&lt;/em&gt; that builds on W.E.B. Du Bois and racial capitalism to connect historical racism in St. Louis with contemporary outcomes across the region. I see this as a natural extension of my prior work and Walter Johnson&amp;rsquo;s historical research. To support this work, I have multiple grants under review and in progress to support the creation of neighborhood-level health outcomes measures in St. Louis and other Missouri cities. These grant proposals address notoriously challenging data and statistical sources of bias for understanding the connections between &amp;ldquo;redlining,&amp;rdquo; historical racism, and contemporary health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project also has substantial community engagement. For example, I have worked with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stlvacancy.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;St. Louis Vacancy Collaborative&lt;/a&gt; to create a &lt;a href=&#34;http://stlvacancytools.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;regularly updated inventory of vacant properties&lt;/a&gt; in the City of St. Louis and am supporting efforts to address vacancy and dumping in the suburb of Kinloch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Open Source Composite Geocoders - Pitfalls and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/geocode-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/geocode-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demographic change, segregation, and the emergence of peripheral spaces in St. Louis, Missouri</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/redlining-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/redlining-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>St. Louis&#39;s &#39;Urban Prairie&#39; - Vacant Land and the Potential for Revitalization</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/vacancy-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/vacancy-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>areal - An R package for areal weighted interpolation</title>
      <link>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/areal-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://chris-prener.github.io/publication/areal-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
